Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, so, let's have a lock.
We're on Thursday, that's Wednesday, Tuesday, Monday.
We open up on Monday, start selling off, no call back.
Start selling off on Tuesday, lost 0.2%.
Finally, on Wednesday, we had the move, right?
By this point, I was assessing the strength of this move.
Again, we'll come to determine how, or, yeah, we'll go over how you assess the strength of a move.
it's starting to show weakness, et cetera.
We'll go over that.
But just for now,
I'm assessing the strength
or the momentum within this move.
It slowly starts to taper off.
Price rips against the strong selling
that we've seen recently.
This was the first short of an opportunity
this whole week in terms of a massive
or a significant swing trade.
So yeah, I've just been waiting for this to happen.
And we got it.
So, yeah, I expected 1-27-50.
because of one reason
and one reason only.
My computer's been really slow today.
I don't know what's going on.
You got many tabs open or anything?
I don't think I've turned his computer off
for like two, three weeks.
It just goes on sleep.
Oh, okay, yeah, yeah.
So basically we called this an extension.
We had this major swing high.
We extended past it.
It almost always fills.
So that was, as soon as we started
to break structure around here,
I was expecting a sell-off.
But again, I don't really follow this conventional market structure break type stuff
where most people who trade market structure like ICT.
So here you have a trend, yeah, they would class this as the structure break, obviously.
Yeah, yeah, looking to short this.
We consider, well, the way I trade, I think this is too late.
I want to be able to see or the way we assess a price move.
we'll be able to see the strength or weakness inside of here
ahead of the high being put in.
Okay.
So there's a certain sequence of events that takes place.
We can assess the strength of this move through that sequence that takes place,
effectively giving us insight into what's likely to happen next
much, much, much earlier than those market structure trade break traders.
So in other words, the trader who sees like, you know, what's going to happen next first,
the earlier you see it
you can make
a logical assumption
or you can logically
you know
reach a conclusion
that that trader
is likely to be better
or he's armed with more
so the whole idea
about walking says
if I said to you tomorrow
or let's say you
as they knew
that within the next hour
or two hours
or 24 hours
a certain piece of information
is going to come out
and it's going to send pound
to I don't know
it's going to either send pound down
or in a certain direction, more than like 2%.
You're going to look to trade that, right?
You're armed with information that the market isn't reflecting as of yet.
So you're certainly in a much better position than the market itself.
That's what you would call informational asymmetry.
Do you have information that everybody else doesn't?
Number one, number two, the market isn't reflecting it yet, therefore is an opportunity.
However, in like 2020, information is very, very quickly and better.
into price almost instantaneously
I'll give you one example
a news headline comes out
before me and you can even
register the headline
Mark price has already moved
yeah yeah
you might have tried to trade
economic data
times so like NFP or whatever it might be
by the time the data has come out
and you've refreshed your page and you've heard the
fucking news or whatever it is
price is already kind of
the volatility is already kicked up and price is already
expanding yeah
yeah so the point I'm making here is the
information that's new, the news that just came out, is very, very, very quickly embedded into
price. Me and you don't have the technological capacity or the speed capacity capabilities to take
advantage of that quick, you know, the price reflecting that information, that information being
embedded into the price. Now, that's all well and good. We're not news traders. I'm not a news trader.
I'm not looking to predict where the market's going to go based on whatever news is going to come out.
point I'm making is speed is
seeing things that the market
is yet to reflect
or having information that the market
isn't yet reflecting is what you call edge
the market is very efficient in reflecting information
very quickly so the capacity for edge
is getting tighter and tighter
the more the market develops and becomes more efficient
in reflecting information
or you're following me.
So if I said to you, then that's the case.
Seeing things early before the market ever affects that,
puts you in a position where you're more likely to have the edge.
Seeing a price move before it unfolds, being able to assess.
So, yeah, seeing a price move before it unfolds before all the other traders,
you affected to have a bigger edge than that.
Being able to see the price move before everybody else,
else you're on board you're basically you have a better edge than then so
circular back to what I would say initially most market structure traders will
consider the break of structure and the retest as a trade what I'm saying is we
have a visual framework and a price framework that we rely on to assess the
strength of any directional move as it's unfolding in real time to contextualize
if it's stronger or weak when it starts
your weakness, when it's likely to start
rotating and reversing well before
the market structure break actually
materializes.
So we can see things before everybody else.
Obviously, it's not all guaranteed, so
even if you get a market structure break, it's not
actually guaranteed that price will sell off from there.
Yeah, it doesn't.
You call that, basically, it ties directly
into probability theory, distribution of outcome is random and probabilities can shift in any given
in any given second really. So if you were to take like a thousand sample, a sample of 1,000
market structure breaks, I'd be willing to say, let's just say, let's give it more parameters.
So a sample of a thousand market structure breaks and this on like, let's say H1 plus, a good,
more than 50% of them would actually materialize into a reversal.
or a big enough trade against the prevailing trend
prior to the market structure break
that you can take advantage of over a large enough sampled set.
You follow me?
Yeah.
So you could argue that a market structure break
has a positive correlation
or a positive expectancy with a reversal.
But take those thousand examples
that you've just found
and line them up chronologically.
So the first one, the first, you know,
market structure break in that sample,
then the second one, then the third one
in chronological order, time-based order.
where you've come to find is that they don't have an even distribution.
So without making it too complicated, 1,000 samples.
Let's just say for argument's sake that it's 60% of the time,
or 60% of those marked structure breaks caused the beginning of reversal,
and 40% of them failed.
So what that means is 600 of these obviously came out as a mark structure breaks
and reversals on 400 of these just failed.
Now, if you were to look at them in chronological order, how those 60, 40% outcomes were distributed,
it wouldn't be the first six in any 10 series reverse, and then the last four in any 10 series don't reverse.
It would actually be just completely randomly distributed.
You might even have, theoretically it's possible, you could have 399 market structure breaks in a row failed to work.
work and then the last 600 work, time after time after time after time they work. Very, very low
probability, but that can be distributed in such a fashion. To make it a bit more simple, yeah,
I give you a coin toss of head and tails, 50-50, yeah, heads, tails. You flip the coin,
what's going to come up as? You don't know. Let's just say it comes up as heads. You flip the
coin again. It's not, you know, this probability is not distributed linearly or, or, you know,
in an even distribution.
So the point I'm making is heads can come up again
and it can continue to come up in a series
even though the actual probability of a head of tails flip is 50-50.
It's only over a large sample set that you're going to get
or that this probability is going to be reflected.
So in other words, we flip a coin 10 times.
It doesn't mean over that 10 flip sample
you had head, tail, head, tail, head, tail, head, head, head, head, head, head, head, head, head, head, head, head, head, ten times in a row, even though the probability is 50-50.
Because then, you know, we're going into the realm of when our probability is reflected in outcomes, it's never over a small sample set.
It's never.
So the 50-50 head and tail flip, you would only get 50% heads and 50% tails over a very large sample set.
all right now the implication of all this stuff is
that you can see a market structure break
and everything can you know your your set up pattern
everything could fit it to a T
but that one outcome you're experiencing
even if it has a 99 to one probability
or 99% chance of working it still
doesn't mean every single time it's going to work
the outcome is distributed randomly
yeah right
we're going to like take a deep dive
to this, I'll show you some charts of like probability outcomes, but the point I'm making here is
outcome, it won't always reflect the probability of whatever you are looking at, and probabilities
can shift in markets at least instantaneously, where one minute ago something was extremely
favorable or a price move in a specific direction was extremely favorable, suddenly it can quickly
reverse or the probabilities can quickly shift because of some new piece of information or whatever.
So we have this dynamic in markets, which is quite unique, I would say.
Probability is a changing all the time.
But, sorry, probably is a changing all the time.
And you have a random distribution of probabilities.
All right.
So your best setups that look perfect, all the parameters are met for that particular set up that you validated is good.
But still, it won't always work.
Or let's just say you found out you've done the maths on it.
You found the necessary samples and you done your data collection
that your Quasemodo or your FTR pattern
has a 70% chance of working, right?
It doesn't mean, you know, just to send this point home,
it doesn't mean that the next seven that you see out of 10 will win
and the next three out of 10 will lose.
You could easily have 10 losers in a row.
The way outcome is distributed has nothing to do with the probability.
It only has something to do with God, bro.
That's the only reason
That's the only explanation that you can give
To why probabilities are distributed randomly
Or how distributed randomly
Only God really decides, yeah
So to white men, I don't say that
Only to you, I would so
Yeah, you can have a 70% set-up
That works every time
But any individual
FTR example that you have
Doesn't have to necessarily affect the outcome
Probability linearly
in other words,
however many times you do it next,
unless you have a large sample set,
it won't be reflecting the 70%.
So the problem where this is,
this dilemma I'm posing in front of you,
you can have amazing setups,
but when you're actually taking that setup next time,
it doesn't mean it will work.
How can we then assess if a setup is likely to work in real time?
Because what I don't want to do is kind of leave it all
to pot-lock chance.
I don't want to have it.
FTR set up that works 70% of the time
and just let the probabilities play out over
a long run because what if
the 70% is reflected over a thousand
trades? Yeah?
But your risk management
your risk management
let's say plan
can't handle 30 losing
trades. Because that's entirely
possible. You might be risking 5%
a time. 5%
if you're losing percent, you know, I don't
how many trades will take in a row,
it will never reach zero, by the way.
Because if you continue to risk
1% of your new equity every single time,
you will never ever hit zero.
You'll eventually hit the lowest point possible
and you can't anymore risk 5%
because a lot of size doesn't go beneath that.
But the point I was making was we have,
yeah, you have this dilemma.
I don't want to leave it up to potlock chance.
there's nothing to say that
this set up over the next
20, 30 trades
won't lose, even if it's a highly
probable, you know, it's a highly probable
setup. So how do we mitigate
that problem? How do we mitigate against that problem?
How do we have, you know, is there a solution for
that, for this issue that we have? Yes,
there is, it's trade management.
We need to be able to assess the likelihood
of the trade working out in lifetime
with a process that's
you know, that's appropriate for the fact that probabilities can change at any given second.
So this is where, again, intimate with all the variations of FTR starts to come in.
What is this, you know, the visual anatomy?
How do they, you know, visually, how do the losing FTR trades look and how do the winning FTR trades look?
and then that's a whole
of a ballpark
of detail
that we're going to get into
so what are the characteristics
of winners and losers
what do they look like
anatomically
visually structurally
what they look like
at what point
is your trade
your particular setup
likely to fail
most of the time
when it fails
where in that sequence
does it fail
what does it look like
what are the variations
in how it can fail
what the variations
in how it can win
what are the dynamics
of managing a trade
when you're taking an entry
an FTR setup
that wins 70% over a large sample
but the next trade I take
I don't know if it will work or not
you know you're going to be
introduced or exposed to this issue
and an issue inside the issue
which is until the trade fails
it looks favourable
yeah yeah yeah that's very true
until the trade
starts to shift and turn
unfavorable it looks favorable
people within that period
you can get quite complacent it's quite actually
it is difficult
psychologically at least when you have money on the line
to court a trade when you want it to win and all this stuff
but this basic introduction to probability theory
doesn't really get too much deeper than this but we'll explain it
in more of a structured way I guess
realizing that each outcome or the next outcome
is entirely separate and independent of the actual probability
because the probability only applies over a large sample
I mean you basically call that a random distribution of outcome
you now have a problem in trading
yeah
we're trying to make money and then we're going to have to come up with the solution
which is basically managing your trade appropriately
and keeps in the same shit
I do this a lot just to kind of send home the point
so yeah bear with me
why do we get on to this
oh we were talking about how we can assess a price move
before it reverses
and kind of assign it a level of probability
whether it's likely to reverse or not
track the strength or weakness of a move
so seeing things before other traders
but just because you'll see
in all the necessary characteristics of a reversal
doesn't mean it will happen
what that requires from you is
constant, constant tracking of price
and constantly reviewing
incoming information
anyway I don't really want to get too ahead of myself
I don't think this is the appropriate
level of discussion at this point
because we haven't already got
into price action yet.
This stuff that I'm talking about
it will be much, much more relevant
to you when I
start to introduce you to the structures and how
we assess the strength or
weakness of a particular unit.
Yeah? Yeah.
Because then you're going to have an issue like
oh, Sully,
you told me about this sequence
that leads to a reversal
but here's two examples
of it not causing a
reversal and it failing, yeah?
And then we're going to talk about, typically that's where we talk about it.
What I say to people, yeah, it's probably not relevant, but you're going to, like I said
to you in the first session, please try to invalidate what I'm saying.
If basically it's a challenge I set for you, try it, you know?
And then what people do is, you know, they're going to come up with, they're going to find
examples of this particular set of circumstances that I say precedes a reversal.
let's just say it's this pattern
and
then they're going to find
like two or three examples when this pattern
did not cause reversal and the actual price
continued.
My combat
against that will be two things.
Here it becomes quite
evident it's not going to work
so you have
the time and the
space to assess
if this is likely to work or not
and this
process of assessing
probabilities in lifetime
is much, much more appropriate
for a complex problem that's random.
You don't know what's going to happen next, so it's random.
So this is having a process that's appropriate for the market.
And secondly, it comes down to things like
just because two out of two examples
in a row didn't work of this particular sequence
doesn't necessarily mean anything
over a large sample set
is your job which I'm going to set out for you
in a task in a kind of a structured way
to experience this over a large sample set
and if you can find the data over a large
or big enough sample set
with this kind of let's say particular
hypothetical pattern
doesn't cause reversal
I'll throw my hands up to be like okay then you're right
but I'm telling like I've had
bare people
even like try to be a bit chirpy
about this stuff
you just over a big enough sample set
can't do it and then the times it doesn't work there is a solution against that there is a countermeasure
against that rather than you know closing your eyes go and taking a long trade and just hoping it
works out that's kind of yeah just in my opinion lower level trade take the trade and just be like
inshallah it works out yeah you know um be like that but tie your camera as well in it
i think yeah yeah yeah i know that saying if you've got the capacity you at the time
or whatever, the chance to get out of a trade
before as soon as it becomes invalid,
there's no point hoping past the point of invalidation.
But yeah, you'll come to find all this stuff.
Bid and ask is what?
Yeah, so.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Bid and ask is the quotes that you see in your screen.
The bid has buy orders there
and ask has sell orders there.
The bid and ask that you see
on a centralized platform.
or on a centralized exchange or a venue,
the bid is the most expensive buy order in the market.
Yeah.
And the ask is the cheapest or the lowest sell order in the market.
Mm-hmm.
Make it up the two most competitive prices available in the whole order book.
Yeah?
Yeah.
That's good for me and you because I only want to buy it at the cheapest price available,
not at this guy's price here or this guy's sell order or this guy's sell order or this guy's
sell order.
I want to buy it at the cheapest price
and obviously I want to sell
at the most expensive buyer
rather than the cheap bidder down there.
Did you get it?
Yeah, yeah.
So that's what you call the best bid
and best offer.
The ask price, sell price.
If I'm offering to sell you something,
that's why I's called an offer.
Best bid, best offer is set by
obviously what quotes or orders
on an exchange.
an exchange exchange is order driven
so it'd be orders wouldn't it
yeah there have to be orders now what type of orders are going to be here
what do you mean by what type
so there's two types of orders one is time sensitive
and one is price sensitive yeah yeah
yeah so these are going to be price sensitive orders
aka limit orders
and
what is another way
way of categorizing limit order traders
passive order
yeah passive and also
price makers yeah
and then obviously
time sensitive traders are urgent
or it's an urgent type of order
it takes limit orders
okay and it takes the available prices
so it's a price
it's aggressive
not passive
what's the other I guess
active but
it's just an aggressive order yeah i think he said urgent urgent order cool um and yeah it's just there's a market
order so the trader who who lifts who lifts this offer or who hits this bidder it's always
going to be a market order seller or a market order buyer so if you buy at the yes price you're
lifting that offer if you sell at the bid price you're hitting that bider yeah now how
does price move them how would i cause this bid and ask price to go up or down respectively on either
side um so it depends like so if you have um a bidder um oh wait these are limits aren't they
sorry which are which are limits um what you're going on about now bid and ask uh yeah yeah so
the bid and ask is setting obviously the price is price making uh i'm seeing
give a bid and ask price
for this special asset
called Zane backed bonds
now
how do I make the price
of those bonds that trade in the
special exchange go up
exchange traded product
how do I make the price of that exchange
traded product go up when it's trading
on a centralized order box
with Best bid best offer
placed by orders
sell orders limit order sorry
how would you make the price of either of those
go up or down or how would you change the best bid best offer which is the price how would you change
them yeah so it's quite simple you know you know the answer it's just i'm making it sound more
complicated than it is here you have asked there's one zane a back to bond there yeah and the next
offer the ask price there's 0.5 zane backed bonds there now if i come in and i buy
market order
price taking order
two
I've caused
basically I've wiped out
the liquidity
at these prices
yeah
yeah yeah
so let's just
pretend
the next offer turns
up here
and that has
three behind it
I've now
drove the best
offer higher
oh okay
yeah yeah
so prices moved up
now in this instance
the spread is widened
yeah
okay so
what is that
principle called when a market order wipes the available liquidity, driving price in specific
direction. Not even a principle. There's a formula for it, but it's basically principle.
Principle. You know, I remember a lot, yeah, but I think it's just the way how
your word things. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I think it is.
Okay, I think you've answered everything. Not to sound rude or anything, just, but look, this is
how you would probably get it.
So I'm not going to give you a hard time, basically.
I'm not giving you a hard time.
The way I'm wording it is the technical way to word it.
And then it's good that things that you don't know you're telling me
so we can explain it or whatnot.
But over time, you'll just, okay, what's, you know,
this principle, it'll make sense, what's there,
you'll never inside out.
And you'll, you know, whatever, what I don't like to do is like,
I don't like to oversimplify things.
I don't like to over-complicate things either.
Yeah.
What it is, is that's what I'll keep it like.
So if these are the technical terms for these type of transactional methods, that's what I'll call it.
I want to just leave it as one.
We're going to discuss everything about it because in a minute, what I'm going to introduce you to you to know, basically we're going to work out how the transactional.
protocols of
each of these different types of orders
when they're slightly different
how they create a very unique environment
which goes against like conventional
thinking of supply and demand
I'm going to introduce you that
I'm going to introduce you to that in a minute
without understanding technically
the individual kind of things around
the different various
or two transactional
methods you would never be able to
reach that conclusion
yeah so if I'm explaining something like
in a lot of detail there's a purpose behind it typically
just to make sure you understand it thoroughly
and then you can make your own
but through understanding something on a deep level
you reach the let's say the next level of truth about it
you can form accurate observations
or you can have accurate observations regarding that
which need no validation from anybody else
because you know what it is technically
does you have the right to kind of like
have an opinion about it
or reach a certain conclusion about it
but what we're going to talk about is factual in a minute
it's not really just an opinion
so this is the kind of reason behind
the level of detail I go into this
it allows you to see things that you probably
or other people don't know about the markets
anyway back to this it's market to limit order ratio greater than one
it drives prices oh okay yeah yeah I knew that
I just I just didn't know that that was the answer kind of thing
yeah I know no so that's a principle
it's your first principle I'm
introduced you to
prices are made
discovered which is basically
prices changing
through this dynamic
through this method of market orders
eating available limit orders
you have to realize
that the makers of the engineers
of markets whenever these orders
were created initially
they thought about the individual protocols
so the parameters
for the different types of orders
and those engineers would have assessed the implication
of how prices will change and move and go up and down
because of these specific methods and rules behind these trading ways
the way you can get in the market
and the way you can get out of the market
the different types of which you can get in the market
these are the main two
these have significant profound
implications on the way prices are set and made.
So in financial markets at least,
a market to limit order ratio of greater than one causes prices prices
to go up or down in an exchange at least.
In a century trade, in a century trade, that's set.
Imagine it was this year, you went to your local shop
to buy, again, milk, but.
and you know you can go to the
you can go to you you can pick the milk up
go to the counter and suddenly just back off
and I'm not no I don't want to buy the milk
you're not you're not locked in
with a market order when you when you click buy
bro and you click I want to buy let's say
three Zane backed bonds
if there's only one available at your desired
price you're going to get filled for one
and the outstanding two
are forced because you're time sensitive
and you're saying
the type of order
you're opting for
is an urgent order
you're locked in,
your next two
are going to get filled
at whatever price possible.
So the cost of a market order
you're getting your time,
your desired,
you know, urgency
in exchange for cost
because the higher cost involved with it.
You might buy one Zane
backed upon that your desired price
but the next two you're looking for
because you're buying a total of three
or like 50, you know, 50 levels above your current price
that you wanted to buy it.
That's the cost you pay for market order.
The opposite is true with limit order.
It's time sensitive. It's cost sensitive.
Sorry, it's price sensitive.
You trade at the price you want to buy or seller.
But what you're paying with is the risk that price may never reach your level.
You get it.
So each of these different trades are trading or transactional
methods have very specific implications on for now on how prices are going to get set.
So we have this liquidity eating order and we have obviously a liquidity making order.
The ratio between them, when the market orders outnumber the available limit orders in a specific
direction, you're going to get a price move.
So let's have a look at the implication.
that let's draw an order book um i won't have to explain everything individually yeah so we know
what the left and the right is yeah these are the prices so we still are a thousand thousand
one two three and then nine hundred and nineteen nine nine eight seven six five four this is the
quantity of orders all lots so fifty
available there, 700 available there, one available there, three available there.
0.1, 4, 3, 2. Limit orders. Obviously, what's quite, what's standing out to you here?
How the one on the left goes from like 50 to, is that 100?
Was that 700?
Whatever you wanted to be.
Yeah, yeah, and then it goes like one and three in the right-hand side.
it's a lot um the numbers are closer together okay yeah so these are quantity of order uh volume available
yeah a quantity of underlying asset available so yeah keep it simple zane backed bonds there's 50 zane back
bonds here because there's a buyer with a buy limit order or there might be 50 different buyers
with one buy order each of um you know of one zane backed bond the point is there is much
much more buy liquidity here than the available sell liquidity there no yeah there loads more
now let's say within the same second so here's one second yeah we'll spread that out over this
arrow so that accounts for one second within that period you had one buyer and one seller come in
that urgent traders with a market order basically the first seller he sold 40
now simultaneously another trader comes in this time he's buying and he simply buys 9.2 who's buying
who's buying more and basically who's transacting more who's bigger bullocks the seller yeah
or the buyer uh the wait the seller is yeah the buyer so the buyer's buying more
basically the buyers
transacting more volume than the seller
no the seller
is transacting 49
yeah yeah
so 49
he gets matched with the first available
bid and the highest bid
there's how much left here
how much money money is left it
one price goes nowhere
simultaneously
this guy buys 20% of them
oh yeah price is going to shoot up
and price
crosses that crosses that
crosses that crosses that and there's still
0.1 outstanding
even though this
guy brought considerably less
if me and you tallied up
how much volume was matched
with a counterpoint there was
orders
49 Zane back to bonds
matched with buyers so that's
trades done
but there was only
9.2 trades done
here and still
still price shot up.
Conventional supply and demand would say the higher the supply
or the more selling than buying,
price should go down if there's more selling than buying.
But the opposite is true.
Yeah, that's a big flaw, isn't it?
No.
It's not necessarily a flaw.
You can make of it what you will.
I think it creates a nice dynamic.
Yeah.
because if one can then consistently
assess which side of this order book is thinner
which side is thinner
the cell liquidity was much thinner
in terms of the total net amount of it there
there was only 9.1 saying back to bonds
here is 154
yeah
if me and you had the data
to consistently assess which side of the order book is thinner
you could deduce logically
which rare price was likely to go
on an extremely
extremely consistent basis
there was an order
there was a study
I'll find the study right now
just give me one second
what was his name
order book
bid ask
price prediction
basically there was a study
a few like
MIT
fucking smart motherfucker's got together
and they looked at data
over historical data
they looked at data for your USD
basically simply looking at the
weaker side of the bid and ask spread
the depth is another word
for available orders on one side
this has a thicker depth
it's much deeper than the depth
of their equity there
they looked at the bidinast depth
and they found that they can make predictions
on where prices are likely to go next
and trade in that direction and make money
I think they simulated an X amount of trades.
They were able to make thousands of trades and bare money
just simply looking at the business depth.
So it brings a high level of, accurate level of,
no, I shouldn't say prediction,
but forecasting ability of where price is likely to go
in the immediate term right now next
if there is an imbalance in the middle and ass depth.
We're going to look at a condition
where we can actually look at it through price
where there's a bit of weakness
on one side of the book
compared to the other
because of some market dynamics
which we're going to start citing
through this session on next session.
Okay.
So the point I'm raising here is
liquidity is weaker on the cell side
in this specific scenario.
Yeah?
Yeah.
We can say, another way of saying that
is sell liquidity is light is the point.
Another way of saying that is
the bidonast debt
is lighter on the ask side
the depth of liquidity here
it is more shallower
than the available by liquidity there
or the less liquid side
is sell side
price in this instance
goes to the less liquid side
even though there's less buying
than selling the price that went to the less liquid side
that's another principle
price goes to the less liquid side
typically because it's easier to reach a market
to limit order
ratio greater than one in the less liquid side, right?
Let me find this because it's going to piss me off, trading research.
What, are you still trying to find the study?
Yeah.
Once you write that down, I'll do this.
So is that like a big principle, then price moves to less liquid side?
Yes, because the probability is in that specific instance or skewed for price moving in a specific
direction. So, you know, let's circle it back to the problem of trading. You try and to
predict what price is going to do next. Yeah. You can be the trader that tries to predict what
price is going to do next, trying to like think in the same way as those large traders who inject
millions and millions a day. We can try to use the same macroeconomic models that they apply
at home trying to think like that. That's an option. Or you can use conventional technical
analysis strategies. There's two different ways. Breakouts or mean reversion. We
discussed a problem with mean reversion technical or indicator based models they're overly refined
to certain environments they stop working with their volatility levels change so problem conventional
breakout strategies they just don't work that often in the markets like today because they're
more efficient basically the market facilitates trade well markets don't break out as much anymore
right the third option sorry the fourth option here is we so outside of all that we we
need edge to consistently predict what price is going to do next to do the so-called thing
trading. I'm telling you an environment where, or an instance in markets where, when there's
weakness on one side of the book, the probabilities are asymmetrically skewed of price going in
one direction over another. By skewed, I mean one-sided. Why? It takes much, much less
volume to push price up to push price down you would need to push price down that's 10 so that's 20%
of that 20 times 5 yeah I think you will need 500% more volume on the sell side than the buy side
in this instance to push price down 500% in this very you know hypothetical so not but I'm just
kind of making it I'm just kind of exaggerating that when the book is skewed
So when there's less liquidity on one side,
the probability is skewed of price moving in a specific direction.
You can even have less fucking volume trading in that direction
and price still goes that way.
If you ask me,
I want to be trading in that circumstance as many times as possible.
Brov, I would bet my, you know,
I would bet like my net worth on it.
I would bet my left leg on it.
I would bet you get it.
I want to do it as many times as possible.
over and over again, because we have a
structure, a market structure
the transactional rules
behind the orders, creating
this dynamic. You get it?
That's a structural
reason for why price goes to a less liquid side.
We're not in this realm
of arbitrary observations about price action
anymore. We're looking at
why price moves in a specific direction over another
because of the actual rules that the market trades in.
The rule set by the market
participants itself.
The market has a tradition in trading.
These are the actual tradition that's been around for Edison's markets are probably
inceptive.
But if you're following what I'm saying, the point I'm raising here is this is a real
valid, you know, a verifiable edge that can't be changed unless the rules of trading
change.
Or this is an effect of the rules that can't be changed unless the trade.
trading rules. So here you have what you could argue is a natural environment based on this
on the market rules where price will go in a specific direction over another because of, again,
the transactional methods. In that circumstance, probabilities of price going to the less liquid side
is skewed and I want to be on that side in the system. Put it this way as well since I add to this
point. The market is something like effects at least. It's going to be getting hit with volume
virtually limitlessly, no, over a big
enough time span at least.
Over a long enough time span, the volume is virtually unlimited.
At any given second, yeah, the volume can dry off.
You can have no volume coming in at times.
But, you know, the likelihood of more volume coming in a specific direction over another
in these environments is quite low.
We'll come to validate that probably today.
We're going to look at why effects.
at least has
multi-directional
trading, buyers and sellers in the same
market virtually all the time.
Outside of all of that,
you have a very simple scenario,
weakness,
on the side of the book, it takes much less volume
to push you up there,
even if simultaneously there's a bigger,
there's a bigger seller.
Now, often what you'll find is
when the book is skewed like this,
you don't even have
that big seller there.
Shit.
You don't even have that big seller there.
So there's hardly any selling going on.
And there's typically going to be a decent bidding going on here.
Right.
But again, not to push ahead too much.
So, yeah, that's a principle.
It gives us an edge in markets.
Sorry.
Yeah, it gives us an edge of markets that's measurable.
But just to say on this point, let me just quickly show you the chart.
I'm not going to tell you what the chart is.
Let's pull it up.
Did you see that?
Yeah, I can see it, yeah.
All right, cool.
It's a chart, yeah?
Yeah.
See higher highs and higher lows.
And then price kind of breaks market structure there, retest, and then sell go.
Could you do technical analysis on that?
You could, isn't it?
Yeah.
I can draw a trend line on that.
yeah definitely
you can probably apply
RSI to that
as a trend line retest
you know what this chore is
bro
no clue at all
what's that
it's a coin toss
chop
coin toss
this is
40,000 coin tosses
so
the trader who was applying
look
they say
it's a coin toss
shop
yeah people could definitely
put a trend line
and stuff on that.
But the problem is, where's your edge then?
What's creating?
Because, you know, the idea in FX or in markets at least is you have a trend
because there's buyers there, buyers consistently bidding it out.
And then here the buyers give in and the seller start pushing this down, no?
That's what the markets are.
But this is a random chart of coin tosses.
Why, you know, you could, one could deduce that that's a trend.
tradable trend line retest
but why did that work?
What's creating that edge?
Is that an edge
or it's just something
that you're observing in a random chart?
Well, if it's coin tossed
then it seems random?
Yeah.
So anybody can sit there
and draw arbitrary random lines
on a fucking chart
and think they have edge there.
What I'm telling you is a condition
which is created from the rules
or as a function of the market rules
and it's like unquestionable environment
where it's not random anymore
if that occurs
you're probabilistically going to get
a move of one direction over another
I'm not saying it's easy to identify though
it's not particularly easy to identify
the weak book
where there's weakness on one side of the book
less liquidity and limit orders
on either side of the bid on ass
it's not necessarily easy
but if and when you can identify it
you have now an edge
over time consistently you'll see price
moving the side of the weaker that's liquidity so this is the kind of point i'm making anybody
can draw lines i think they found trends a three-year-old could yeah um the problem with this is
this is only one instance of this trend line retest kind of thing working would it work consistently
if i turned this 40,000 coin toss flipchre into unlimited coin toss so we just watched it for the
rest of our trading career.
Let's just, you know, forget, let's just, you know, it's not trading anymore.
We're looking at coin tossers trying to make money of the distribution of coin tossing.
What you'll come to find is, I would bet at least that these fucking, you know,
the technical analysis doesn't really work consistently over the long, over a long sample set.
The only way to trade an infinity charm of coin tosses would be to mean revert.
so it's very unlikely that price would run
not price
because what happened here is you had
heads heads heads heads heads heads heads heads
and then tails tells tells tells
it's very unlikely you could work out some
like probabilistic there could be
I don't know if you know but there's something called a belker
yeah this is where most of the outcomes
this is like how far or this covers seven
70% of the coin tosses or the outcomes of the coin tosses.
And this will be like the outlier scenarios.
So 30, 15%.
In these instances, you're going to have the extreme scenarios
where you get heads, for example,
that's 150 times, yeah?
Where you get heads a thousand times in a row.
That's going to be an outlier scenario.
Whenever an outlier scenario goes on,
you could try to let's say there was a way to trade going to toss charts
you could try to shore it back to this mean value
over the long run I would think that would work
but still it's quite random there's no edge there
all I'm doing is I'm playing the fact that it's 50 50% probability
yeah um so yeah
there's no edge to to random arbitrary bullshit like this
typically this is what most traders are trying to do
they don't have any edge they just fucking doing some random shit on charts yeah
that's mad because I thought it was something
like it was an FX chart
bro even
what baffles me about this is
how
even in FX
we're going to look at something like this
called a break of midflow it's technically called
a break of midflow you don't have to understand what it
means but it's just called a break of midflow
it's the first sign of weakness
of this whole movie
and it's happening in a fucking
in a coin toss chart
the only kind of explanation I have for
it is when you
I used to have an explanation
what is it when you
I'm gonna have to think of it
me and my mate went through this one time
they sat down like why the fuck does this happen
yeah we came over like
it'll probably just come in your head randomly
yeah it will
it's something to do with
the like
the tendencies of random distribution
it was something long those lines
but oh I'll ask me
um
who's got enough patience to do
40,000 coin
You can simulate it
Oh, can you? Okay, okay
Yeah
We can simulate anything really
Equity
Right, so
Let's just say you start with
This doesn't really matter
It's 50-50 yeah
So heads 50%
The tails 50%
If you know
If head comes up you win one
If tails comes up
You win you win one
We're going to do it
A thousand times
And we're going to do
20 different coins
a thousand times each
what you'll find is
this is the mean
average
of the
the 20 different
coins
here's an outlier scenario
where heads came up
1,800 times
or yeah
1,000 no
we forget the number
yeah
because that's compound
that's fucking making
1% on 1%
forget that
but where heads came up more
and then here's an outlier scenario where tails came up more
but what you can see in this instance here is
that the bulk of the outcomes end up in the middle
yeah definitely
and then you have a few outlier scenarios here
that's with a 50 to 50% probability
and you you know each outcome is equal in terms of
heads is just one and then tails is just one
yeah it's still possible that with this shit no edge type type parameters i guess that if god was
blessing you you would have been that guy there you get it yeah god just blessed you well
everything went your way even though you didn't went you weren't really that good yeah or even though
your probabilities of like make let's just say i said to you look every single time heads comes up we're gonna flip a coin tomorrow
or today
its heads
and tails
his opinion
every time
heads comes up
I give you a pound
every time
tails comes up
you give me a pound
if you were this
gold line
you would have made
a decent amount of money
you know
you would have made
you started with
basically
because you started
with a grand
but forget
you start on a ground
you start on zero
you still
made 800
that's crazy
right
because what this is
showing you is
in this instance
that if you were
this gold
line 800 times things went your way or not even that uh i think collectively by that point
yeah man that's crazy bro that's only like 900 coin tosses happened by them and you're on 800 that's
fucking crazy well yeah that is pretty mad actually yeah so that's what you call random distribution
of outcome every outcome is random distributed now obviously if you have now now
let's just say the coin
it was a cheat coin
one side the head side is heavier
than tails but you didn't tell me
or I didn't tell you that
yeah now
let's just say heads coming up
there was an 80% chance of that
versus tails
and every time
yeah there was an 80% chance of that
now watch where these lines are going to go
they're still going to be randomly distributed
but skewed
can you see the variation between
this 50, 50%
is quite high.
There's a large variance.
Yeah?
The outlier scenarios,
one's massively negative,
one's massively positive.
The variance is going to tighten up.
You get it?
They're still randomly distributed.
One of those lines is going to be like
a multi-fucking millionaire type.
And then one of those lines is going to be the lagger.
But, yeah,
Roan has done as well as the best line.
Anyway, I'll show you.
There you go.
Yeah, that's not.
So now you have better odds of winning.
Still, you could have been that guy who made a thousand trades and you,
I guess that's not that bad.
Why is that?
You made nearly a few hundred grand, two fifty one, two seventy grand.
And then with the other guy who had the exact same problem like odds as you,
God blessed him with six hundred grand, double you, triple, nearly triple.
Or no, more than double you.
Although you had the same odds, though.
It was crazy.
So again, this is more just talking about how things are randomly distributed
and that ties directly into what we're talking about how.
Coin flip chart, you need edge.
When you're trading to the less liquid side,
when the order book is thinner on one side,
so here's a visual of the thickness in the bi-liquity,
and here's a visual of the slight, you know, the thickness of the celliquity.
the buy liquidity is much thicker than they sell liquidity
the probabilities of price going up versus down
or enough volume coming in on the buy side
that causes a market to limit order ratio greater than one
before the necessary sell volume comes in
you follow me yeah
the buy side is skewed
obviously not 80% but there's instances
at the right part of the price
where the probabilities are on
it's like impossible if the price to continue
in that instance there
but the problem is like
even though the probabilities might be let's just say
90% that price would go up or the versus down
because the book is so thin
imagine how little volume it takes to push price up
and how quickly that volume will come in
in other words price won't spend a long time in that area there where the probabilities are most skewed
where the book is the thinnest on the cell side you follow me yeah um so that becomes an issue
trying to take advantage of these price behaviors but oh sorry this in this instance in price
but that's solved through skill building skill um forget 80% right you probably want to be more
realistic of i call it a 50% win-loss ratio but with four to one
this guy makes it
a killing
an absolute killing
the way I see it
yeah
if you're that guy
you could
probably walk in the street
you'll find a million pound
everything you do
would turn to gold
yeah just look everywhere
but it is what it is
America
it's your kiss not bro
it is
anyway
let's go back
to this lesson
and I do have
more to cover
the main
the main lesson
right now has been
you can have more
buying than selling
and price goes to the one
less liquid side
as a function of what
you know what's the formula that kind of
create that allows that to happen
markets limit order ratio
oh yeah yeah of equal
to all usually greater than one
yeah
it's easier to reach
one market limit order ratio
if there's only you know
three fucking limit orders on one side
versus 5,000 on the open
yeah
um
very important
so these are going to
at least for now second the tone
for price movement
this is the reason you're going to see
price drive higher
is because typically there's going to be
thinness on the cell side
and enough volume
eating the buyers
enough volume
eating the sellers right
some of the stuff I want to talk to you about
it's this notion
that limit orders
or liquidity obviously
equity is orders
that me and you can
transact with aggressively
and in other words
limit orders
could be considered friction
so if we are approaching
the price is approaching a level
and there's a whole
whole whole bunch of
set limit orders here
this fucking
600 billion worth of sell limit orders there
assuming
those orders don't
get removed how will price get through that level it's a question oh it's question um so all of all of
that is uh is orders there limit orders yeah the 600 billion of sell limit orders
how will price get past that level would it need to keep eating at it yeah you need 600
you need 600 billion to get borrowed yeah assuming that nobody removes their sell orders there
yeah it's quite simple so liquidity is friction you can't get through this area without eating away at it right yeah
anyway that's enough of that that was something that i want to just talk to you about let's circle back to
an order book we know in exchange it's everybody at one table yeah it's a single table that
everybody sits at it's got unlimited seats really and um not unlimited seats but like you can
you can trade through this guy who's a bow card and access this and you can have unlimited
clients but anyway it's a single venue a single table it's a single order book is one
price set by the best bid best offer order driven exchange we started to discuss last week how in a
OTC market, it's pretty much similar.
Yeah, it's pretty much the same.
So it's similar in the sense that you can source the cheapest price if you want from anybody.
So we're looking at cars.
We can go to one car dealer, second car dealer, third car dealer, four car dealer.
Or we're looking at the price of milk, yeah.
But let's just keep the cars for a minute.
So this dealer buys a car of you, which is a Fiat Ponto.
So you go to the dealer, you want to sell it.
You sell it for, I don't know, 400.
He will buy the offer of you for 400, yeah?
You guys negotiate it.
Fiatonto.
Sell.
And then the dealer is now bought a Fiat unto for 400.
The customer comes in, me, I want to buy a Fiat Ponto.
The dealer will what?
Sell it to you.
Yeah, for maybe five people.
So the dealer brought off you for,
cheap and sold to me
for more expensive. He did what?
He set his own bid and ass,
no? Yeah. That's his
bid, that's his ass. He
built inventory. He got rid
of the inventory and he captured the
difference, which is the spread.
Now obviously, if we're looking at multiple
dealers in a row, this
guy can't be too much of a fucking idiot
and
let's just say you have two
fee up on terms of sell.
You got rid of one of the first dealer.
He didn't want to buy the second, so you go to the next dealer.
And you start negotiating a price with him.
Why?
It's over-the-counter.
It's private.
It's a private negotiation bilateral between you and the counterparty.
That's it.
Nobody else is involved.
It's just bilateral.
There's two people alone.
So you go to the next dealer, you have to negotiate with him again.
You have to chat to him, have a coffee, whatever.
The price, this deal is a bit tapped.
So you sell the Fiat Ponto to them, and you manage to negotiate.
share price of 700.
This decade is going to sell,
sorry, buy your Pia Ponto of you,
the 700.
Let's just assume
before you went to this dealer number two,
you already went to dealer one,
and you know, dealer one for you
rang his boys at dealer three and dealer four.
And they were all willing to bid off you
for
401,
470.
This guy is the most expensive
bidder
yeah right
now imagine
you had let's say
the capability to check
all four of these dealers
prices at any given second
which would be the best bid
yeah you'd go to
do number two wouldn't you
that's it so his
his
his bid
turns out to be the best bid
and that's what you would see
on this special
let's say office you have
that's connected to all the dealers
and taking prices from them
that would be the best bid
and simultaneously
if you want
they're willing to sell you a Fiatonto
this guy because he's buying at 700
he might be only willing
to sell at 750
nobody comes and lifts that off
he's massively outpriced himself
he's bought for the most expensive
to make a profit he has to sell at the most expensive
you might buy off it
so you might sell to him
now he's he's brought
a Fiat Ponto of you
he can only make profit
right
if somebody else comes
and takes that Pia Ponto
right
yeah
because then he captures the spread
he sold here
sorry he brought here
and he sold there
but realistically
you know you're doing your market research
you can see that this deal
is a fucking retard or I comment this stuff
that means you are using the same technology
I comment now I want to buy a Fiat Ponto
he has one
obviously because he brought one of you
this guy has one
he brought off you
which one am I going to go to
number one
he's got the best offer
now this guy
remains holding an inventory
of one fee up on toe
brought for too much
and he has to get rid of it
he can wait for ever and ever
and ever and ever
for someone to come and lift his offer
at 750
but it's very unlikely
that someone will
as long as the other dealers
keep pricing him out
so this guy is not
competitive. He's a fucking idiot. Number one, number two, the risk is that Fiat Ponto
suddenly, let's just pretend the diesel and Theresa May said, they're not going to use diesel
cars anymore. This guy's holding a fucking inventory of these cars. He might start to get super
desperate to get rid of that fucking Fiat Ponto. Yeah. I'm going to start looking at how his
behavior can cause prices to move and how, how, yeah, we'll look at that.
And then we're going to actually start to apply it to real market environments.
But before any of this, we have multiple dealers here, one, two, three, four.
They're all quoting individually.
You can have the technology, which takes the best bid their stuff, or fund them,
and virtually creates the same kind of dynamic that you get on a single order book.
It's important to note, though, that each of these banks run,
oh, sorry, dealers run their own order book internally, right?
And you can aggregate all those orders off, or those that book up into a single box,
basically called an aggregated book.
That's all the time.
That's what FX basically is.
That's what over-the-counter is.
You have multiple venues, no central place, it's all privately negotiators.
Now, in essence, it's the same.
The main difference here is that these are not bona fide orders.
They're not necessarily limit orders.
even if there are limit orders
the dealers have a provision
in the contract
that you sign
when you buy the car offer
they have a provision
in that contract that says
even if we're offering you a price
even if we accept
your money
we can give it back to you
and reject the order
that's called
last look
so a dealer
has a quote
for Fiat Ponto
for Fiaton for
400. You go to him to sell to him. He's like, yeah, I'll buy off you for 400. You shake
can, you exchange cash. He starts giving you the car. You're about to get in the car and drive off.
But because in the contractor says he has last lock, he can turn around with that note.
This is the one price. You can either buy it off you for 350 or you can fuck off.
It's not fit, but the dealer has that provision. Now, the reason he might have.
have that is, let's take it back to this example
where Dealer 2 massively
outpriced himself. Yeah?
So you're there, bro?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So dealer 2, you go to
DL2, you sell him the Fiat Ponto,
he says, okay, I'll buy you for 700.
Within that time, he clocks
that his counterparty, or his counterpart,
his competitor, is bidding
for 400.
And simultaneously,
if this dealer 2 buys
at 700, he can own the best offer that he can sell at is cheaper than where he's buying
that. Yeah. So he's going to be forced to accept a loss, except the loss. He can quickly turn
around like, no, fuck you, we don't want to buy it for 700. We're only willing to buy it for
the best prevailing bid market-wide. So he can reject your order or he can use this provision
called Last Look. In other words, he kind of has the capacity to always back out of unprofitable
transactions ahead of time. That doesn't mean he won't be in unprofitable transactions. He will
because of something else that I'll introduce you to a minute. It's called price change,
which you know what I is. On this basis, at least, a pricing error where he has priced himself
out, he's not competitive anymore, he can mitigate against that through Last Look.
Now, let's forget that.
Let's forget last lock doesn't exist
because it is a real scenario
with the dealers holding onto inventory
that you can't get rid of all.
This guy's just brought for 700.
He's bought Fia Pono,
and this guy's also brought up here upon him.
Here's dealer three.
His offers are $5.50.
His bids are $397.
what's the problem
they're all
different
that's fine
they're all going to be different yeah
because that's maybe
maybe they're pricing based on their own view
of where fia pontos are going to be
and the
the independent private demand they get
from their customers over the last year
they're pricing the way they price
the problem is this motherfucker
he's buying fia pontes for 700
yeah but then yeah he's not going to get any back
well the same back
it's unlikely now that somebody's going to
you know, somebody's going to come and lift his offer at 7.50.
So he's not going to be able to get rid of his Fiat Ponto.
And if he gets, you know, let's say that's the dynamo.
There's other news comes out and Fiat Puntas are suddenly turned to shit.
There's a, there's that exhaust scandal going on with Ponto's now.
Suddenly all these dealers start to get rid of their punters.
So this guy, he aggressively, or forget that?
Yeah, yeah.
So this guy aggressively sells his Fiat Ponto.
He can sell it to this guy.
Yeah?
Because he's got an offer there.
He quickly sells to it.
Let's just say he saw the news first.
Now this guy, he clocks that his competitor, the dealer won,
quickly just got rid of him in an urgent way of Fiat Ponto.
Now this guy's long, sorry, what the fuck am I talking about?
he's
he brought one
he needs to sell
the Fia Ponto
he can only sell
it at this guy's bid
sorry I'm being an idiot
he has to accept
a $3 loss
so he brought
our 400 of you
he quickly goes to
the dealer 3
he's willing to accept
$3 loss
he sells that
now this dealer
3 has brought
a Fia Ponto
at 397
no
yeah
he clocks that
dealer number 1
which is his
competitor
as quickly
and aggressively got rid of Fiat Ponto
at a loss
so he maybe says
I don't want to be in fucking
I don't want to hold Fiat Pantas
anymore as well
he quickly clocks the news
he also
aggressively
offloads
his Fiat Ponto
works out for him though
yeah so it works out for him
but the point I'm making here
yeah let's just forget
this guy's prices
let's just pretend he was competitive
for a minute
let's even assume
this guy lost
one or two dollars
on that transaction
or like one or two
ten dollars on that car
what we've seen here is
information
because this guy
suddenly didn't want to hold on to
Tia Ponto's and he was a direct
competitor of all these other guys
when he aggressively
offloaded his inventory
information was
interpreted from this guy's actions
resulting in my man over here
getting rid of his infantry as well
and then information from him
because he's also a competitor of this motherfucker
would further
result in this guy be like
oh all these guys are getting rid of their punters
I want to get rid of my punter
and he would offload to the dealer number four
and then that would go to five
then that will go to six
then that will go to seven
all of these guys
for one reason and one reason only
not because they're taking necessarily
you know short positions
because they want to fuck Zane stop loss over
but they just don't want to
hold on to this toxic inventory
as a result of new information that's come out.
It doesn't even have to be news.
It could be a customer order.
We'll get into that in a minute, yeah?
But this information has leaked from one to three to two to four to seven to nine.
And all of these guys suddenly and uniformly sequentially sell, sell, sell, sell, sell, sell,
causing price to do what?
one side of the book?
Yeah.
Do you think simultaneously,
the dealers who provide the service
of providing liquidity, basically,
when they start to see each other selling,
do you think they're going to be bid as well?
Do you think if we were to aggregate
all of their available by liquidity,
do you think the book's going to be super, super thick here
and millions and millions and millions
are going to be available?
No, definitely not.
You're willing to buy.
No, the liquidity will see.
suddenly sees up the willingness
for these dealers who provide
by liquidity and sell liquidity
their willingness to be bidders
in this market was suddenly
you dry out. So now you have a dynamic
where there's
selling going on. The Fiat punters
are being chuffed around by hot potatoes.
Nobody wants to hold it.
It's a murder weapon or something.
And simultaneously, nobody wants to
buy it as well.
So you have a thin buck
extra selling going on and price drives lower.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Yeah.
As a direct function of information leakage from a dealer's
hot potato trading they will get amongst each other.
It's not prevalent in 2020, today's markets anymore.
There is an element of it, but typically it's not a major thing.
We'll come to find out why.
It's just a piece of information I'm giving you
how information leakage of one dealer managing his,
his infantry risk can cause a price move.
It's called hot potato trading
where nobody wants to hold on to that infantry
or one Fiat Punter.
It might be, literally might be this.
Zane came in
and every single time this dealer trades with Zane
and buys a car off him,
turns out to be shit.
Maybe he's like he's got a bad omen.
This dealer, he feels like, yo,
it feels like he's got boudoir
with his fucking Fiat Ponto.
So he buys,
it of you, but it quickly gets rid
aggressively. Yeah. When that first
action again, rid aggressively, that's it.
Sets off that chain reaction.
Of information leakage.
So, there's a huge
problem in markets, at least, in this
instance. Wait, when
information starts to be
interpreted or leaked,
amongst
informed, the deal is
informed about via punters at least, because he
receives much more
business buying cars and selling
cars than the average joke.
So one could make a logical,
through logical deduction,
you could assume the dealer knows more about fear
upon the other than anybody else.
Informed counterparties between themselves,
if information starts a leak amongst them,
it can result in this chain reaction type event
where price accelerates in a certain direction,
simultaneously you have weakness created on that side,
and volatility can subsequently increase.
Price starts on.
jump in that direction, drive in that direction.
So hiding information is a necessity to keep market stable as best you can.
Nobody wants to get rid of, nobody wants to reveal the information.
But you have a dynamic where sometimes they have to.
Before I let you go, I want you to remember that and write it down if you can.
Before I let you go, I just want to validate something, yeah?
Last session we talked about how a dealer's job is just to simply develop.
provide a service, you know, they provide predictable immediacy.
If I'm buying milk, the shop provides me predictable immediacy.
He's my liquidity provider.
He sourced the milk and he sold it to me at a premium.
He made a spread.
In markets, at least, the dealers are just doing the same.
They're providing you a bit of an ass quote virtually all the time, not all the time.
There should be all the time, which basically means they're willing to be your counterparty all
of the time, take on your risk, give you the liquidity. Why? Because they capture the spread.
No? The most profitable thing for any dealer would be, let's just take this car dealer,
that a million buyers came, sorry, a million people came to sell him Fiat Ponto at price 400.
And a million people simultaneously came to buy a Fiaton Tau of him for price 500. So he can capture the $100
dollar spread every time. But the problem with that is, it's all well and good in this fake
static scenario. What if price moves? What if a million people sell him a Fiat Ponto? And then suddenly
the better, you know, price starts selling. And nobody wants to buy Fiat Puntas at 500 anymore.
They're only willing to buy down that to be a number. This guy now brought Ponto's, a million
punters of 400. Nobody is lifting his offer at five. Price is sold off quickly. And he's not holding
on to toxic inventory he has inventory risk he's holding on to a million
fiat ponchos and he can only get rid of them at a lower price is fucked maybe as
price is dropping from 500 to 399 he also turns into a seller to get rid of his
inventory no so we're going to look at other options they have are we're going to start
to apply it to actual market so just need to give you a small breakdown of fx structure
and then we'll get into it.
FX structure, the evolution of FX
is OTC now. And next session, I'm going to ask you
what's the difference between OTC best bid, best offer, and best
offer in an exchange.
I'm going to ask you what's the best thing about a dealer.
So what is the most desirable state for a dealer?
Give me an example of information leakage.
These will be some general generic questions.
Look, again, there's no pressure because I talk shit at you for two hours.
you're just listening to me
for now at least
it has become more interactive
but just for now
I have to give you the basis
yeah yeah
that's understandable
so you know
when you said
the example
is that like real life
no
give me an instance
where information leakage
causes
um
hot potato trade
yeah
okay that's fine
just explain
how potato trading
you could apply it to a real life
scenario
information leakage
I'll give you an example
Imagine you could get
Donald Trump's press leakage
Press information 10 minutes
before these talks
I guarantee you I'd be a millionaire
Yeah you want easily
Easily yeah
That's a form of information
That's the actual leakage
Yeah
What about if you rent
Retail is different
A retail estate
Real estate is a different
there's information
leakage and everything
if we I can
the best I can do
is explain it
through an order book
because in your life
what could I
deduce from someone's actions
that would make me change
my behaviour
I'd love to think about that one
it's going to be an obvious
an obvious example
but anyway
if we're looking at order book
the simplest form
of information leakage would be
not even information leakage
but the simplest form
updating information would be
if we had a total of 30 million here initially,
or 30 lots, 30 lots,
and a total of, I don't think it's the right sign,
but a total of 20 lots here.
And then the next minute,
suddenly a large buy limit order came in,
and this turned into 2,000 lots.
Would you want to be a seller in this amount?
No, no, no.
It was 20 lots first and 30 lots sell equity.
and the next minute
there are a huge, huge
bio that comes into play
and it turns into
2,000 lots total
definitely not
you would not want to hit the bid there
no no
no
maybe you probably want to
fucking buy
right
people
have you heard of Nav Singh
Nav Singh
Indian guy
he made 75 million dollars
he called
2010 financial crisis
flash crash
oh yeah yeah I've heard of
He wiped two, he wiped like a trillion dollars off of markets that day.
It wasn't him.
They blamed him, yeah?
Yeah.
He would play this dynamic where he would layer the book with, let's say,
excessive orders on one side.
And that would create a response in the market because other people would respond
to this information.
He would make it look as if there was excess supply of demand at one side
and the market would respond because it's constant.
reviewing incoming information
you get it yeah
so there is on a central
trade of assets this top
order book dynamic
where a power game
is going on a chair you know a can
mouse game is going on
information is being revealed hidden
this fake information
and this guy he was putting
fake information into the
tricky album but yeah we'll talk
about that in due time
so basically what he was doing here is called layering
he would
his sell orders
his buy orders
he would layer the book
so this is the top of
this is the best offer best bid
he had a
I guess an algorithm
which would place
a huge sell order
a minimum of X percentage
away from the best offer
so it would never get hit
in other words
let's just pretend
that this is two price levels away
if this best offer
moved up by one price level
this would also move up by one price level
to maintain that two price level distance
you get it
yeah and basically whenever he
put that fake order in there
he would make it seem as if what
there's a massive seller in the market
he would only do that
on times with his selling going on anyway
and that would add to the momentum
he would short it basically and write it down
take two three four ticks
get out he made a
like a hundred thousand dollars a day
for a period
just by trick in the market
for four ticks
he at one point accounted for I think
don't quote me on this but I think
more than 20% of the daily
volume on S&P 500
in 2007
that's crazy
one of the most
liquid contract in the world
in futures at least
he fucking out he
accounted for a major
percentage of the volume in that day
but he did over stuff as well
he did spoofing so he had another algorithm
that would place
an order here and
when HFTs
try to quickly snap up
his order I think
he would quickly cancel
that and buy into them and cause price
to move against them so mad shit like that
and it would all happen obviously
but then it was algorithms doing it
he can't really do it that quickly
nor me and you anyway
he probably was trained
to he was autistic as well
he severely fucking fucked up in his mind
you can do shit we can't do
what happened to that money that he's
made did the government like
he got scammed he got scammed he got scammed yeah
but although he was good at
trading he was a bit more
vulnerable I guess or gullible in real life
so people like gave him and gave him advice
for shoddy investments
they told him buy gold
like have a gold money company here
do this
have a solar
you know wind turbine company
in Scotland
everyone bumped him
he got bumped
but but all of that money
he lost it bro
he had 70
he made 70 million
he was a multi millionaire
he used to drive a bike
as in like a
a bicycle bro
he used to live upstairs
in his one bedroom
and they didn't know
he's a million
because
he saw
the market as a game.
Yeah, like a literal game?
In that sense, yeah.
The game he was playing, the cat and mouse game, it was, it is, but if me and you made
a hundred grand within a day, do you think you'd be risking a hundred grand tomorrow?
No, definitely not.
He would.
That's your whole equity.
He did things like that.
That's why guys like him, they make big dollar in short months' time.
Normal people don't do that.
don't get me wrong
you can be the outlier scenario guy
where God blesses you and things go your way
and you know
if you're this blue line
you're going to short it the day a flash crash
happens and you're going to bank a dollar
and it will just run them
you can be that guy
or it could be one of these
outlier scenarios through autistic skill
and you don't care about money
you've got big bollocks and you put on risk
and still things go your way
you can be this nobody down here
that tried to be that the big bollocks
no risk guy
and things didn't go your way
you get it
or you can be the more
in between meeting you guys
because just naturally
personality wise
you know
there's a certain limit
to how much money you can make
without like
or lose without
emotions
before your psychological
state deteriorates
at least in the immediate short term
so that is typically
most people
these guys up here there's a look and combined with madness and equally these guys down
here they're mad but they're just less lucky